So I have a question. So what is the so
to say value or is there any value in
dealing with so to say some theoretical
aspects of dharma
not those that to say um directly
interact with greed and aversion so to
say so that's say even questions like if if
so that's say even questions like if if
god exists or not
let's say or any other like materialism
and whatever else Well, um,
Well, um,
when it comes to those very kind of
abstract theoretical things,
especially when you cannot verify them
for yourself, like it's it's going to be
to some extent based on speculation,
those are always the things that the the
in the sutras, the Buddha would say that
those are not the those are not the
things that he declares because they're
not uh fundamental to the holy life. So,
um it's it's it's actually better
to refrain from finding an answer to
that type of question
rather than finding the answer that kind
of corresponds to dharma. Because
if you were to, like you said, emphasize
the freedom from greed, aversion, and
delusion aspect,
eventually you would realize that the
only reason that you sought an answer to
the question or that you thought that
the question was important is because
somehow you thought that it it was going
to help you resolve your suffering
somehow or or because it was itself,
let's say, rooted in greed in some form
of greed, aversion, or delusion. So when
that goes away, it's like you wouldn't
have an answer to the question, but the
question wouldn't appear to you as
important. At least this kind of
question. Other ones like um let's say
rebirth or
um I don't know other realms and things
like that. uh you would then actually
have um more practical basis to see what
the Buddha meant when he referred to
those things whereas initially you would
just kind of be taking it on faith. So
you would for example be able to see how
craving inevitably means that
if you die
like it it cannot be it cannot have um a
beginning. It's not something that can
sort of have popped up
at some point out of nowhere and then
kind of continued um by its own
momentum. So, but all of those things
initially it's like rather than trying
to to figure it out how it works or or
how it would be, it's if you discern
your own mind and you see these things
directly for yourself
by freeing yourself from the five
hindrances and greed, a diversion and
delusion, then you would have the quote
unquote right answer, which from the
initial perspective, what you expected
an answer to be probably would feel like
inadequate. But now it doesn't because
you're not subject to all those doubts
and pressures which are really mostly
emotional rather than purely
intellectual.
Yeah. what you mentioned about like
craving and re I mean like the fact that
craving have no beginning
that doesn't imply also that kind of
there is no magic hand so to say like
there is no like
like craving doesn't will not end by
itself somehow in the future.
Yeah. You would also come to realize
that like because
it's a it's something that when you when
you discern it in like through practice
through graduate training virtue uh
sensory restraint seclusion
it becomes apparent how every craving
that you ever have
can only be there because previously
like when your mind is subject to
craving even though you don't want it to
be subject to craving um it's always
because In the past, you were acting out
of some kind of pressure of that mind
that made it worse. It's like a fire
that without some fuel having been
provided at some point that fire that fire could
at some point that fire that fire could
not possibly be burning right now.
So like having a fire that just started
like you just come and and there's a
fire there. Nobody lit it. Nobody did
anything. It's just a fire there. you
realize that's inconceivable. But again,
like it's it's it would actually be better to
it's it's it would actually be better to
put the question aside
rather than just receive that as an
answer because then you would still be
kind of um intellectually believing in
something that
it might it might actually stop you from
really making the effort to see it for
yourself because you find safety in the
intellectual answer. So
it's it's kind of like remaining in that
um
almost harder position of acknowledging
like okay well whichever answer I find
it's going to be like I'm it would only
be adequate if I decide to settle for
it. I could always question it further.
So then instead of of
finding safety in those answers, you
look for the real safety, which is
freedom from craving. And that's why
like the the noble truths u weren't like
pronouncements about the nature of the
universe, but rather about the thing
that would want you to make to that
would make you want to know about the
nature of the universe. That those were
the noble truths. Um,
so entirely internal quote unquote if
you want to put it that way.
And also like when when the Buddha said
um that somebody who who understands
rightly would come to see that the the
arising of the world, the sess well the
world the arising of the world, the
sessation of the world is found within
this very body. no larger than 2 m. Um
because factually you would you were
going to see that all those notions that
you might have as as kind of lofty and
grandiose as it might be. If you
investigate even on a
on a very kind of coarse level, you
realize like okay there is a kind of
bodily pressure
that's making me want to think those
things and I wouldn't want you I
wouldn't be able to think about those
things if I was let's say u very sleepy
or very tired. So you realize like even
on a very mundane level of reflection
all of these things don't kind of
somehow you cannot access something apart from
you cannot access something apart from
your six sense basis.
So you instead put that first and see
everything else through that. Like uh if
it's a sight, sound, smell, taste,
touch, uh mental thought or image or
phenomenon. Um you look at it through that lens
Um you look at it through that lens
instead of emphasizing the content of
and making it special because it's a
thought about God, a thought about the
universe, thought about this. You see,
okay. Well, however special it is in its
content, this has also arisen within
this um
um
six sense body within this um was it
what what was the word? The
path. No, but but the the word was like
carcass like carcass the the the
body like it's it's within this and you
don't have to deny any any content of
the ideas that you might have because
that's not where the solution lies.
solution lies in just becoming fully
established in the knowledge that oh
this dharma has arisen
and that's how you develop this passion
like could you talk a little bit more
about this passion because can easily be
like kind of taken as it's something
that I have to do that I have to
actively try to develop but it's more like on the
try to develop but it's more like on the
level of discerning
the right kind of context as you were
talking about before.
Yeah. Well, you can use that example as
well. If you
um don't see it on the right level and
you just take this passion as another
mental phenomenon, you kind of take it
to be right because the content is
right. you would overlook the fact that
well I have passion towards this now
like this passion has become the thing
that I am obsessed with almost and then
you realize well that cannot possibly be
like it's going to be there to some
extent initially when you don't see your
mind clearly but the whole point is you
want to reach the point where um that
dispassion becomes as you said something
that you discern something that's there
in the things already not something that
you have to manufacture because that's a
that's a contradiction in terms. If you
were truly indifferent, if you were
truly dispassionate, what need would
there be to fabricate anything? Um, so
how do you practically discern that
dispassion? Well, you have multiple
ways. Like anything that prevents you
from fundamentally having that that
special privilege over the rest of your
experience is uh reveals to you that instead of
is uh reveals to you that instead of
like denying your sense of control and
denying your
uh the input that you have over your
experience, it becomes
um contained within something that's
fundamentally not in your control. So if
you have developed passion towards this
passion, let's say, you ask yourself,
okay, well, could I be contemplating and
and doing all of this this passion if I
didn't have this body here right now? If
I didn't have all these even these ideas
that I have about this passion and so
on, those ideas need to be arisen first
in order for me to attend to them. If I
were to forget all about that for some
reason, I wouldn't be able to cultivate
anything anymore. So see that dispassion
now is not on your own terms. It's not
like it it cannot be now under lain by
your desire because it's now kind of
comes underneath whichever standpoint
you take. This is before that and that's
the that's when you develop like well
right view because
The basically what what what
you would have when you just have a kind
of selfmade quote unquote dispassion is
that view of of um annihilationism or
non-existence. Like even if you don't necessarily go to
Like even if you don't necessarily go to
the point of like asserting that
um nothing exists, nothing is real and
everything will disintegrate when when
the body breaks apart. And the sutas
would say which is was kind of the most
extreme version of that view.
If you have that kind of um attitude
that takes
denial of things as automatically
more pure, you would fail to see that
well that is now the thing that I am
passionately established in. So that's
that wouldn't be the right view. Like
the right view is when you undercut even
that through the right discernment of
well you could take whichever angle but
craving for example like instead of what
what would you why would you develop
this passion on the wrong level
practically? Why? Why?
Why? Why?
Why would you develop dispassion on the
wrong level?
Like why would you be kind of
passionately doing the dispassion? Let's
put it that way.
Well, because to some extent I try to do
it and I don't see my doing in the
things. Uhhuh. But what what do you not see
Uhhuh. But what what do you not see
specifically?
Well, I don't see my involvement in the
in the things. I don't see myself
basically doing
that. I don't see.
Yeah. Yeah. That's one angle. Uh but but
Yeah. That's one angle. Uh but but
specifically, let's say um
is there something that
let's say in relation to craving
that you're not seeing?
Because see, you you can be thinking in
terms of um that would be kind of the
the the common thread of this passion.
It's like you want to abandon craving,
you want to abandon lust, abandon greed,
and you're trying to do that like
generally. It's not that that you're
kind of
being lazy or something. You're making
making effort.
But what is it that you're not seeing in
regard to that specific craving that
would be a problem?
I try to get something from that
conversation like I try to trade like
somehow I try to Yeah. I try to get
something. Yeah. So, so but with the craving is it
Yeah. So, so but with the craving is it
is it like
where do you find craving basically?
Because see you you would be when you
when you have when you're trying quote
unquote to do the dispassion
you have a notion of craving
otherwise how how what would you be
directing yourself towards
that's what I was going to say is the
the craving that you are
trying to squish you could say is
um well it's not the craving that is
actually kind of controlling you at that
moment. You see something and you have some idea
You see something and you have some idea
of what craving is, but that is within
the actual craving. So, it's going to be
well, it's going to be rooted in you not
seeing craving for what it actually is.
You're going to be focused in on
something that fits your idea of what
craving is.
And that is going to be too narrow, so to
that is going to be too narrow, so to
speak.
Um, so, so what's the what is the problem
so, so what's the what is the problem
there with that notion of craving that
you have?
Is it just that it's too narrow or is
there something more
well direct that that makes it an issue?
Let me try to
think of what I mean by too narrow
because sometimes let's say let's give
an example like I could um let's say
craving towards food and I could develop
a view that like well as the James
actually did like somebody somebody
might have at some point realized like
um oh yeah I'm craving towards food it's
it's it induces sensuality in my mind so
So they decide okay well this is clearly
a problem. So if I want to abandon
craving I need to abandon food
um
or anything else like specific types of
thoughts when people would say I
shouldn't think about the future because
that's that's kind of um
craving. Yeah, it's craving. I shouldn't
have memories about the past and
remember things I did or
is it what I didn't like?
And that would be like uh trying to make
the dispassion
like trying to force. Yeah, it would be.
It would be. But specifically, there's a
like a kind of wrong notion there that
that even if you let's say um no matter
what anybody tells you, unless you fix
that wrong notion, you're still going to
put the emphasis in the wrong place.
I was kind of trying to think of a more
um original way of saying it, but like
you are
you're focused on the content of it.
You're not
Yeah. You're not seeing it on the level of
You're not seeing it on the level of
your actual attitude.
Yeah. Even if you recognize like factually
Even if you recognize like factually
you're you have recognized your attitude
in these things before.
Mhm. And like factually you've seen okay like
And like factually you've seen okay like
this is craving. You're going to be
tying that actual recognition of what
craving is to what you were doing at the
time. Mhm. Um, so yeah, the danger there
is when you then recollect that was
craving before that's now another
thought.
So can that's so that doesn't
necessarily mean that that's not a
craving now.
So that that thought is going to stand
for craving in your experience. Well,
basically the the problem is that you
you would have developed a
you would have started to think about
it's almost it's basically inevitable
like when you don't see the form of
juice like you will have assumed or or
established an objective notion
of what craving is basically that that
even if you are looking at your attitude
it's all within the context of you But
you see, I'm sure when somebody has that
view, they would be kind of feeling like
they have the craving in their mind when
they contemplate food or or when they
eat food. Otherwise, why would they keep
keep doing it? It would become clear
like, oh, well, I free myself of
craving. But no, it actually continues
to feel like, yeah, that craving is
there. But the the issue is like by
putting the emphasis on the
blanket view that you developed
beforehand, you don't realize that
actually yes, there might be some
craving for food. But the thing that's
really supporting that whole setup of a
mind that's passionate in the most
general sense is that craving of you
doing this whole thing to begin with.
It's like you overlooking your attitude
of could be restlessness, could be
doubt, could be any kind of um
thing that's controlling you from behind
supposedly making you do something good
and wholesome. In other words, abandon
craving for food. But actually, it is
the more fundamental unh wholesome thing
that's kind of um
uh how would you say that? Like u
the driving force. Yeah. It's it's it's
it's it's what's underneath like
you say it's like the theme of what
you're doing.
Yeah. It's it's like when the sutas
would describe
uh you don't grasp at signs and features
that will lead to the arising of longing
and aversion. Um I think often people
would understand that is like precisely
in this context like food. If I see a
cake that has a nice shape or something,
I shouldn't either ideally I shouldn't
look at the cake at all. If I look at
it, I should somehow play with those
perceptions so that they don't I don't
recognize like it's just a shape. It's
not really really a delicious cake. It's
just a brown shape. But actually the
sign and feature is that theme
that you would that theme might not be
there at that moment. You're suppressing
it. Let's say the theme of this food is
agreeable is nice. I want more of it.
It's delightful. That's a that's not a a
um kind of thing that you're telling
yourself. It's the implication
of the thoughts that you would be having
when you're actually acting out of
craving for uh the cake. Those would be
the the kind of um yeah themes that are
underlying your whole mental activity
around this thing. But now in this
context, let's say of somebody who just
developed that blanket view of rejecting
um food because food is is rooted in
craving. The sign and feature there of
the theme that they're developing
basically or or establishing themselves
in is a is a theme of aversion, theme of
restlessness, theme of um denial. and
they don't see that as a sign or feature
that leads to the arising of states of
um distress of agitation.
And so
that's what that's what it that's what
it means to because see this the sut
doesn't say um he doesn't look at sites
on account of which lust and aversion
would arise.
That's almost presupposed if you're
keeping virtue and have some common
sense. It's even much more subtle than that.
It's even much more subtle than that.
It's having seen a sight, having heard a
sound, having smell the smell. He
doesn't grasp at signs and features on
account of which unh wholesome states
will arise. So it's it's that's that's
already at a level where you wouldn't be
attending to those things like pull on
carelessly. um because that that already comes
um because that that already comes
within the virtue basically like like
it's just obvious this is taking you
towards breaking a precept you wouldn't
be um attending to it um he
neededlessly. So now within that
when there are things that are let's say
not unh wholesome to look at nor not unh
unh wholesome to look at nor not unh
wholesome to smell not unh wholesome to
taste now you have to look at what are the
now you have to look at what are the
themes the background themes that I am
maintaining in regard to this whatever object I'm
in regard to this whatever object I'm
engaging with uh and and those themes
are it's it's not Again, it's it's
important to emphasize that it's
something that that's that becomes
apparent like it's it's it's
like it's it's it's
preverbal, let's say. It's not like a
like a thing that you are um saying to
yourself. It's it's the most kind of
acute subtle context behind this whole
situation.
You could almost look at it as like a
very coarse example of it would be like
the the motivation
when you're doing something like if
you're talking to someone
and you're let's say using very polite
language on the outside
but actually your ulterior motive there.
you're not necessarily thinking that in
your mind like um that let's say I'm
angry towards this person and I really u
despise what they did but I'm I'm I'm
trying to I'm acting out of that anger
but I'm talking to them in a very polite
way because I hope that through that
they will not do that thing that I don't
want them to do again. So that whole
sign and feature, that whole theme that
you're not necessarily aware of is a
theme of aversion even though on that
external level you might not even be
clear to yourself about the fact that
that's the theme. Um so those are that's
what the Buddha meant with with grasping
signs and features. And in this context
going back to what we were describing,
you would have to extend this principle
to anything.
And that's how you would start to
abandon these views because you would
realize like well there's no value in
this if even if it's the right thing that I
if even if it's the right thing that I
thought I got from the Buddha there's no
value in in cultivating something that
leads to the increase of lust or leads
to the increase of aversion. If it does
that means that's not what the Buddha
was actually actually meant. Um
so then you would start to see that um
yeah the the actual this passion is a
theme that's at that background level on
the level of mind of the level of chitta
you start to realize like okay there's
there's absolutely no benefit if I am
thinking thoughts about death and
thoughts about sickness and thoughts
about losing everything. If the mind, if
that animal that's kind of indirectly
there at the same time, but but it's not
the thoughts. if that animal is getting
actually agitated and
less pliable on account of you thinking those
pliable on account of you thinking those
thoughts.
Of course, it might be startly kind of
um
off-putting to reflect on those things, but then
to reflect on those things, but then
that's something that you would begin to
be able to distinguish for yourself like
what's the right type of sana of being
moved by something as the Buddha said,
things that are worth being moved by.
What's the difference between that and
just winding myself up for no for no
purpose? Because you see the the wrong type of
Because you see the the wrong type of
winding yourself up, let's say,
would be more restlessness.
No, but but actually you would realize
like if I stop doing this, I actually
more inclined towards the no states
than than the opposite.
Can you say that again? the the wrong
kind of working yourself
like like if you're just thinking about
death, thinking about sickness, think
thinking about aging
like time kind of.
Yeah. But but not paying any attention
at all to like how what is the attitude
behind this.
You kind of just assume that that
contemplation in itself is right
mechanically. Yeah. Exact like like a mantra almost.
Yeah. Exact like like a mantra almost.
um
you just
by doing that you would be um
you would be putting yourself in a
position you're you're acting out of
hindrances. So actually your mind would be like
So actually your mind would be like
right now it's focused on this because
you're forcefully keeping it there. But
if you were to bring let's say let it
loose and and go wherever it wants you
would find that the unh wholesome unh
wholesome directions have been either
maintained or maybe even increased
because you were acting out of the
hindrances. Whereas if you were doing it
with some recognition of like okay no my
mind was actually obsessed with life and
and intoxicated intoxicated with life
intoxicated with youth intoxicating with
intoxicated with health as would say and
based on having recognized that theme
you cultivate this opposite theme then
it's like yeah you might factually feel
a sense of like um urgency a sense of of
disenchantment even like like almost
like uh to the point of of uh being
moved by it like oh I should be more
heatful. I should be more careful with
my actions. But see that is now actually
taking you away from the hindrances.
It's it's it's it's leading you in the
direction of in the right direction and
it's even if it's not let's say
perfectly peaceful as it would be to
just ignore that you would that you are
subject to these things it is um leading
to a decrease of unh wholesome states
overall. So that's why it's like um that
similarity of the cook actually the the
Chinese version has a has a very uh nice
passage that doesn't occur in the potty
one and actually it was the the very
thing that we were discussing in that
sign of the mind talk. It's like if the
cook presents a uh dish to the king based on
presents a uh dish to the king based on
his own ideas, his preconceived notions
of what the king should be eating rather
than actually paying attention to the
preferences of the king and where the
where he inclines. then that's why he
will never be able to um basically be a
good cook and get promote promoted and
rewarded by the king. So it's that same
thing like you have on account of
reading on account of contemplating you
have developed a blanket view
that this food that this type of
contemplation is good because you know
it's about death it's about sickness.
Okay, sure there are probably worse
things to think about, but if you do it
without paying any attention to where
you're you're at, your whole attitude
behind it and you're not even aware,
like I said, that there was some
intoxication that there was some wrong
attitude there and just you're just
doing it because because the Buddha said
I should do this.
You are cooking for yourself.
Exactly. Not for the human.
Not for the human.
Exactly.
So that's why you want to it doesn't
matter what the the contemplation is.
Um especially when you're not
sufficiently familiar with the science
of your mind and and you haven't got the
right view yet. You should the the your
main contemplation should be like what's
my attitude behind this
because that's what will keep you in
check and see if you are doubtful like
well I'm not sure what my attitude
behind this is well you should actually
redirect your effort to clarifying that
most of the time rather than just
continuing to because what are you going
to be um making foods like cooking
dishes uh with based on probability like I I I
uh with based on probability like I I I
think this one is more likely to well no
it's better to actually okay well
instead of doing this let me look at the
king and see what's actually going on
what the mind really needs
yeah like what what the mind needs in
terms of if it has been inclining in you
actually see it inclining in the wrong
direction and you realize okay now
contemplating death will take it away
from that wrong direction but if you
just don't know And you just keep doing
it, you will be inevitably you will be
winding yourself up unnecessarily
because there is no need to make effort
unless there are unh wholesome states
present that that becomes your unh wholesome
that that becomes your unh wholesome
state your restlessness
because so that's that's exactly why the
Buddha said like you have four right
strivings you have abandoning arisen and
wholesome states you You have making
sure that unarrison state unh wholesome
states don't arise. You have making sure
that uh wholesome states arise and
making sure that wholesome states are
maintained. So that's an effort in and
of itself. And if you only do the other
three, something's going to be wrong because
something's going to be wrong because
sometimes you have a at least more
wholesome state of mind where there
isn't anything um harmful at the time.
And you need to be able to recognize
that and and learn how to protect it
rather than constantly assuming like no
no there must be something unwanted.
It's like no the king needs more food
just by default. He needs he needs more.
Um well no sometimes he just had enough
and that's that's good for now.